<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE riscos-prm PUBLIC "-//Gerph//DTD PRM documentation 1.02//EN"
                            "http://gerph.org/dtd/102/prm.dtd">

<riscos-prm>
<chapter title="Filing system drive information">
<section title="Introduction">
<p>
Filing systems may be based on devices which are able to be changed dynamically in use ('hot pluggable').
These devices may issue an UpCall to indicate that a device is now available, or has become
unavailable.
</p>
</section>


<section title="Technical details">
<p>
Two UpCalls are used to indicate that a filing system path residing on a device is now available,
or has been made unavailable:
</p>
<p>
<list>
    <item><reference type='upcall' name="DriveAdded"/></item>
    <item><reference type='upcall' name="DriveRemoved"/></item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Not all devices and filing systems issue these UpCalls, so clients should treat them as
    advisory.
</p>
</section>


<section title="UpCalls">

<upcall-definition name="DriveAdded"
                   number="18"
                    description="A filing system may be available on a given path.">
<entry>
 <register-use number="0">24 (&hex;18)</register-use>
 <register-use number="1">Pointer to a zero-terminated filing system path prefix for a new device</register-use>
</entry>

<exit>
 <register-use number="0-1" state="preserved" />
</exit>

<use>
<p>This UpCall is issued by a device when filing system path has been made available.
    This may happen due to a new disc being inserted, a device being formatted, or a remote
    system becoming available.</p>
<p>At the time that the UpCall is issued the filing system path should be accessible through
   normal filing system operations. The nature of hot pluggable systems mean that by the time
   this call is received, the device may have already become unavailable, or the filing system
   on the device may not be present.</p>
<p>The filing system path takes the form of a filing system name, a disc name specification
    and an optional path specification. For some devices, the disc name may be a number,
    indicating that no name has been determined yet, or that there is no name available. For
    others, a name may be given. It is recommended that the path be canonicalised to obtain
    the correct name of the device.</p>
<p>Example prefix names:</p>
<p>
<list>
    <item><code>ADFS::4</code></item>
    <item><code>SDFS::0</code></item>
    <item><code>Share::Storage</code></item>
    <item><code>HostFS::Host.$.Mountpoint</code></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>This UpCall must not be claimed.</p>
</use>

<related>
<reference type="upcall" name="DriveRemoved" />
</related>

</upcall-definition>

<upcall-definition name="DriveRemoved"
                   number="19"
                    description="A filing system is no longer available on a given path.">
<entry>
 <register-use number="0">25 (&hex;19)</register-use>
 <register-use number="1">Pointer to a zero-terminated filing system path prefix for a new device</register-use>
</entry>

<exit>
 <register-use number="0-1" state="preserved" />
</exit>

<use>
<p>This UpCall is issued by a device when filing system path is no longer available.
    This may happen due to a disc being removed, a device being formatted, or a remote
    system becoming unavailable.</p>
<p>At the time that the UpCall is issued the filing system path will not be accessible and
    no further information is available. As such, clients should attempt to track the
    paths to which the drive may refer. In particular, devices may refer to drive numbers,
    without any name being canonicalised, and clients may therefore need to track which
    drive numbers refer to which canonicalised disc names.</p>
<p>This UpCall must not be claimed.</p>
</use>

<related>
<reference type="upcall" name="DriveAdded" />
</related>

</upcall-definition>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- MetaData -->
<meta>
 <maintainer>
  <email name="Gerph" address="gerph@gerph.org" />
 </maintainer>
 <disclaimer>
    <p>
        &copy; Gerph, 2021.
    </p>
 </disclaimer>

 <history>
  <revision number="1" author="Gerph" date="23 Dev 2021" title="Initial version">
    <change>Created from examples of sources using it.</change>
  </revision>
 </history>

 <related>
    <reference type='link' href="https://gitlab.riscosopen.org/RiscOS/Sources/FileSys/SDFS/SDFS/-/blob/master/c/service" />
    <reference type='link' href="https://gitlab.riscosopen.org/RiscOS/Sources/FileSys/ADFS/ADFSFiler/-/blob/master/s/ADFSFiler#L1055" />
 </related>
</meta>
</riscos-prm>
