<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE riscos-prm PUBLIC "-//Gerph//DTD PRM documentation 1.02//EN"
                            "http://gerph.org/dtd/102/prm.dtd">

<riscos-prm>
<chapter title="Iconbar priorities">
<section title="Introduction">
<p>
Iconbar priorities have been vague at best, with some usages being declared
to be the 'easiest way to do things'. In addition to this, some entities
such as ADFSFiler have used incorrect iconbar priorities by accident. This
particular case means that Floppy discs do not appear where they are
documented to appear in the PRMs. Floppies are documented to appear at
&hex;60000000. They actually appear at &hex;70000000. ShareFS used a priority of
&hex;68000000. This results in a mismatched iconbar, where the three cases of
documentation, logical appearance and prior use cannot be resolved
simultaneously.</p>
<p>
Thus, it has been decided to clarify the usage of parts of
the iconbar. This should make for a more logical system, and the possibility
of multi-tier iconbars and other such changes.
</p>
</section>


<section title="Technical details">
<p>
These categorisations provided here amend and expand on documentation provided in the PRMs.
The intent is to clarify the system for a logically organised iconbar, with
clearly defined positioning for components, and whilst retaining the current
state wherever possible.
</p>

<p>
The iconbar should be viewed as:
</p>

<p>
<image src="iconpriorities.png" type='png' caption="Iconbar layout"/>
</p>

<subsection title="Object sources and sinks">

<p>
These are icons for devices to which objects can be sent or retrieved from.
They are ordered logically from read only devices on the left through
read/write devices to write only devices towards the right. Alongside write
only devices are the volatile devices; those devices whose contents are not
likely to remain permanent from session to session (or even within a session).
</p>

<p>
The full ordering is:
</p>

<p>
<value-table head-number="Priority">
    <value number="&hex;76000000" name="Scanners"><p>Read-only device</p></value>
    <value number="&hex;74000000" name="CD-ROM"><p>Read-only device</p></value>
    <value number="&hex;70000000" name="Hard disc"><p>Read-write device<br/>Examples: Any fixed RW medium falls into this category</p></value>
    <value number="&hex;68000000" name="Floppies"><p>Read-write device<br/>Examples: Any removable RW medium falls into this category</p></value>
    <value number="&hex;60000000" name="Network"><p>Read-write/Read-only device<br/>Examples: Any network filing system falls into this category</p></value>
    <value number="&hex;40000000" name="Volatiles"><p>Read-write device<br/>Examples: RAMFS, Transient, Trash cans, Memphis, Scrap, etc</p></value>
    <value number="&hex;0F000000" name="Printers"><p>Write-only device</p></value>
    <value number="&hex;04000000" name="Accelerators"><p>Examples: ResourceFS, "Pinned" items, Director, Menon, etc.</p></value>
</value-table>
</p>

The "Accelerator" applications are considered virtual devices.

<p>
All devices in this category should have a name underneath, ideally
identifying the medium name with which they are associated. If no medium is
associated (eg. a removable, or unconfigured device), they should display
the medium name (eg. Zip disc, Printer, LanMan, etc), or a generalised
medium identifier (eg. the drive or port number).
</p>

<p>
These applications should not provide a "Quit" option.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection title="Data source / sink controllers">

<p>
This is basically a place for internet servers, connection systems and
other network utilities to live, as well as local servers. Like [1],
these should have their name under them. Samba, TelnetD, Newsbase,
InetSuite, WebServe and Netplex would fall into this category. These will
grow to the right when the user loads a new controller.
</p>

<p>
These applications should provide "Quit" options. Most should provide a
status window, and many will provide configuration windows.
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection title="User applications">

<p>
This is where user applications appear when loaded. They will grow
to the left as they are loaded, taking up the free gap space.
</p>

<p>
These applications should provide a "Quit" option.
</p>

<p>
They should not have text placed under them unless they are configured
into a particular state that must be described. Such applications are
discouraged unless there is a genuine need.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection title="System control applications">
<p>
This is where system control applications live. These are things that
will control the machine, the desktop or the way in which the system
works. Initially, this comprises the Task Manager and Display Manager.
Because of its high priority, Help lives here too. This may be
rationalised in future.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>

</chapter>

<!-- MetaData -->
<meta>
 <maintainer>
  <email name="Gerph" address="gerph@gerph.org" />
 </maintainer>
 <disclaimer>
    <p>
        &copy; Gerph, 2021.
    </p>
 </disclaimer>

 <history>
  <revision number="1" author="Gerph" date="12 Jan 2022" title="Initial version">
    <change>Created from original Select documentation.</change>
  </revision>
 </history>

 <related>
    <reference type='link' href="http://www.riscos.com/support/developers/riscos6/desktop/wimp/iconbarpriorities.html" />
 </related>
</meta>
</riscos-prm>
