<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE riscos-prm PUBLIC "-//Gerph//DTD PRM documentation 1.02//EN"
                            "http://gerph.org/dtd/102/prm.dtd">

<riscos-prm>
<chapter title="DCI Driver Link Status">
<section title="Introduction">
<p>
Under the DCI, network device drivers must announce their presence through
<reference type='service' name="DCIDriverStatus" href='?'/>. It is assumed that devices announcing
themselves in this way are available for use. The device may become
unavailable, most likely due to link loss (such as a cable being
disconnected) or memory shortage. No indication is available to the user
as to the state of the device from the driver.
</p>

<p>
    In order to allow notifications of such states to be provided to the user
(and to other clients who may need to be aware of network infrastructure
changes), it is proposed that the service call be extended. Authors should
consult the DCI driver specification or the Internet chapter within PRM 5a
for more details of the current interface. In summary,
Service_DCIDriverStatus is issued by drivers to announce startup (reason 0)
and shutdown (reason 1) of a driver and its associated DIB (Device
Information Block).
</p>

<p>
This has been extended to include announcement of link status changes (<reference type='service' name="DCIDriverStatus" reason="2"/>). Two
new reason codes are to be used for this purpose.
</p>

</section>

<section title="Service calls">

<service-definition name="DCIDriverStatus"
                    number="9D"
                    reason='2'
                    reasonname='LinkActive'
                    description="Notification that the link provided by a DCI driver has become active">
<entry>
 <register-use number="0">Pointer to <reference type="subsection" name="Device Information Block" href='?'/></register-use>
 <register-use number="1">&hex;9D (reason code)</register-use>
 <register-use number="2">2 (sub-reason code)</register-use>
 <register-use number="3">DCI version supported</register-use>
</entry>

<exit>
 <register-use number="0-3" state="preserved" />
</exit>

<use>
<p>This service is issued to announce changes to a Device Driver. An 'active
link' indicates that the device driver is capable of sending and receiving
data. An 'inactive link' will never send or receive data. This mirrors the
use of the DCI statistics flag. For compatibility with devices which are not
aware of these new reason codes, all modules should assume that a newly
started device driver has an active link. It follows that any device which
starts up and is aware of these new reason codes must issue the 'link
inactive' (reason code 3) service if its link is not available.
</p>

<p>
Expected uses for this service:
</p>
<p>
    <list>
        <item>
  Dynamic address configuration in presence of new network infrastructure
    (eg ZeroConf address re-announcement, DHCP lease renewal)</item>
        <item>
  User notification of network absence
    (eg Notifier protocol)</item>
    </list>
</p>

<p>
Non-module clients, and module clients wishing to obtain more information
about the state of the link should query the statistics for the DCI driver
in the usual manner.
</p>

<p>
Drivers may, but are not required to, defer announcement of inactive links
if their physical state is such that transient failures (in the order of
seconds) may occur. Drivers which can detect the physical nature of the
network to which they are connected must signal a link state change when
they detect such a change (eg configuration changes to a wireless network
SSID, encryption key, channel, etc).
</p>

<p>
Clients should expect that any 'link inactive' notification may indicate
that the previous network connection is invalid. On 'link active'
notification, clients may attempt to re-establish connections to remote
systems.
</p>

<p>
Clients should attempt to use the existing connections before restarting a
lengthy negotiation or configuration process. Where confidential information
is involved, clients should not attempt to re-establish any connection
without first confirming the action with the user.</p>

</use>

<related>
<reference type='service' name='DCIDriverStatus' reason='3'/>
</related>

</service-definition>
</section>


<service-definition name="DCIDriverStatus"
                    number="9D"
                    reason='3'
                    reasonname='LinkInactive'
                    description="Notification that the link provided by a DCI driver has become inactive">
<entry>
 <register-use number="0">Pointer to <reference type="subsection" name="Device Information Block" href='?'/></register-use>
 <register-use number="1">&hex;9D (reason code)</register-use>
 <register-use number="2">3 (sub-reason code)</register-use>
 <register-use number="3">DCI version supported</register-use>
</entry>

<exit>
 <register-use number="0-3" state="preserved" />
</exit>

<use>
    <p>As described in <reference type='service' name='DCIDriverStatus' reason='2'/>.</p>
</use>


<related>
<reference type='service' name='DCIDriverStatus' reason='2'/>
</related>

</service-definition>

</chapter>

<!-- MetaData -->
<meta>
 <maintainer>
  <email name="Gerph" address="gerph@gerph.org" />
 </maintainer>
 <disclaimer>
    <p>
        &copy; Gerph, 2021.
    </p>
 </disclaimer>

 <history>
  <revision number="1" author="Gerph" date="30 Dec 2021" title="Initial version">
    <change>Created from original Select documentation</change>
  </revision>
 </history>

 <related>
    <reference type='link' href="" />
 </related>
</meta>
</riscos-prm>
